I want to negotiate a deal with you.
มาคุยการค้ากันหน่อย
Can these things
ของพวกนี้
be made?
ทำได้หรือเปล่า
I need them the day after tomorrow.
มะรืนนี้ต้องใช้แล้ว
Do you think I'm omnipotent?
ท่านคิดว่าข้าเป็นเทพเซียนหรือไร
Signal arrows, fire thunderstone, and sleeve daggers.
ลูกดอกทะลวงเมฆา ระเบิดเพลิง มีดพก
You think these things
ของพวกนี้
can be conjured up just like that?
นึกจะเสกก็เสกออกมาได้หรือ
You and Yuan Xiaoliu can make it in time.
เจ้ากับหยวนเสี่ยวลิ่วช่วยกันทำ ทันอยู่แล้ว
I'll pay extra. Double.
ข้าจะเพิ่มเงินให้ สองเท่า
Triple.
สามเท่า
I can't afford any more.
มากกว่านี้ไม่ได้แล้วนะ
Discussing money between friends makes things awkward.
เป็นสหายกันพูดเรื่องเงินทอง มันห่างเหินเกินไป
You know what I want the most.
ท่านก็รู้ว่าข้าต้องการอะไรที่สุด
Alright, I promise you.
ได้ ข้ารับปากเจ้า
Li Lejun won't be chosen for a political marriage.
หลี่เล่อจวินจะไม่ถูกเลือก ไปสมรสเชื่อมสัมพันธ์
Deal.
ตกลง
Are these the places you and Yizhi
นี่คือสถานที่ที่เจ้ากับอี้จือ
want to travel to in the future?
จะไปท่องเที่ยวในอนาคตหรือ
Yes, these are all places I want to visit.
ใช่แล้ว ล้วนเป็นที่ที่ข้าอยากไปทั้งนั้น
Master Yuan told me
ในสถานที่เหล่านี้มีสองสามแห่ง
there are special ores
ที่อาจารย์หยวนบอกข้าว่า
in some of these places.
มีแร่ชนิดพิเศษอยู่
It sounds very interesting.
ฟังดูน่าสนใจมากเลย
I want to take a look.
ข้าอยากไปดูสักหน่อย
Here, here,
ตรงนี้ ตรงนี้
and here.
แล้วก็ตรงนี้
There are bandits at the border. Be careful.
แถบชายแดนมีโจรชุกชุม ต้องระวังด้วย
If it's convenient for you,
ถ้าเจ้าสะดวก
you can tell me the route you are going to take.
บอกเส้นทางที่พวกเจ้าจะไปให้ข้าก็ได้
There is a geomancer in the army,
ในกองทัพมีอาจารย์ฮวงจุ้ย
who can draw a detailed map
สามารถวาดแผนที่อย่างละเอียดให้ได้
to avoid any omissions.
จะได้ไม่พลาดอะไรไป
Xiao Wuyi,
เซียวอู๋อี
having you as a friend
การได้ท่านเป็นสหาย
is a true treasure.
เหมือนได้ครอบครองสมบัติร้อยอย่าง
Then when the time comes,
งั้นพอถึงตอนนั้น
can I also use your name
ข้าใช้ชื่อของท่านไปขอพัก
to stay in the Beifu Army Camp?
ในค่ายทหารเป๋ยฝู่ได้หรือไม่
In your dreams.
ฝันไปเถอะ
You are not a military family member.
เจ้าไม่ใช่ญาติทหารสักหน่อย
Don't even think about taking advantage of me.
อย่าคิดจะมาเอาเปรียบข้า
[Key to the Phoenix Heart]
[ชะตารักกระดูกปักษา]
[Episode 11]
[ตอนที่ 11]
Wuyi.
อู๋อี
Congratulations.
ยินดีด้วยนะ
You had a great victory today.
วันนี้ชนะอย่างยิ่งใหญ่เลย
How is Da?
อาต้าเป็นอย่างไรบ้าง
He was injured by an arrow,
ถูกลูกดอกยิง
but his life is not in danger.
แต่ไม่เป็นอันตรายถึงชีวิต
He made contributions in this battle.
เขาสร้างผลงานในศึกครั้งนี้
His Majesty has agreed to transfer him to the Imperial Guard.
ฝ่าบาทเลยทรงรับปากให้ย้ายเข้า หน่วยทหารรักษาพระองค์
He will be back by my side soon.
อีกไม่นานก็จะได้กลับมาอยู่ข้างกายข้าแล้ว
That's good.
งั้นก็ดีแล้ว
When did you start planning
เรื่องของคนเลี้ยงสัตว์เหอซี
the matter of Heximu?
เจ้าเริ่มวางแผนตั้งแต่เมื่อใด
Before returning to Jiankang.
ก่อนกลับเจี้ยนคัง
That's our Wuyi,
อู๋อีของพวกเรา
never missing a single detail.
คำนวณไว้ไม่พลาดจริง ๆ
Now, the Eagle King
ตอนนี้อิงอ๋องนั่น
has also been forced by you
ก็ถูกเจ้าบีบจน
to sit down and have a good talk.
ต้องมานั่งคุยกันดี ๆ แล้ว
Wuyi.
อู๋อี
If I want to contend with you,
ถ้าข้าอยากจะสู้กับเจ้าสักตั้ง
do I have the qualifications?
ข้ามีสิทธิ์หรือไม่
The Eagle King bet the three prefectures,
อิงอ๋องเดิมพันด้วยดินแดนสามเมือง
and I bet the name of Beifu.
ข้าเดิมพันด้วยชื่อเสียงของเป๋ยฝู่
What are you fighting for?
แล้วอี้จือล่ะสู้ไปเพื่ออะไร
What is the bet?
ของเดิมพันคืออะไร
I don't know.
ไม่รู้สิ
Perhaps after a fight,
บางทีอาจจะต้องรอให้สู้กันเสร็จก่อน
I will understand.
ข้าถึงจะเข้าใจ
I saw everything in the martial arts arena today.
วันนี้ที่ลานประลองยุทธ์ข้าเห็นหมดแล้ว
You like Xie Jiayu?
เจ้าชอบเซี่ยเจียอวี๋
Yes.
ใช่
You are shameless.
เจ้ามันไร้ยางอาย
Before I knew she was the one you love,
ก่อนที่ข้าจะรู้ว่านางเป็นคนที่เจ้าชอบ
I had fallen in love with Xie Jiayu at first sight.
ข้าก็ตกหลุมรักเซี่ยเจียอวี๋ ตั้งแต่แรกพบแล้ว
But you are my best friend.
แต่เจ้าเป็นสหายคนสนิทของข้า
And now you know.
ตอนนี้เจ้าก็รู้แล้วนี่
So I have done nothing now.
ดังนั้นตอนนี้ข้าถึงไม่ได้ทำอะไร
She is still waiting to leave with you.
นางยังคงรอที่จะไปพร้อมเจ้า
You're the one who doesn't want to leave.
เป็นเจ้าเองที่ไม่คิดจะไป
So what if I am?
แล้วจะทำไมล่ะ
I'm betting Xie Jiayu
ธนูดอกนี้ในวันนี้
on this arrow.
ข้าขอเดิมพันด้วยเซี่ยเจียอวี๋
Xie Jiayu is a person.
เซี่ยเจียอวี๋เป็นคน
She has feelings
นางมีความรู้สึก
and a life of her own.
มีชีวิตเป็นของตัวเอง
She shouldn't sacrifice for anyone
นางไม่ควรต้องเสียสละเพื่อใคร
or be controlled by anyone.
หรือถูกใครบงการ
Yizhi,
อี้จือ
you told me this yourself.
นี่คือสิ่งที่เจ้าบอกข้าเองนะ
Whether to stay or leave
จะไปหรืออยู่
is up to you.
เจ้าตัดสินใจเอง
Whether Xie Jiayu stays or leaves
เซี่ยเจียอวี๋จะไปหรืออยู่
is up to her as well.
ก็ให้นางเป็นคนตัดสินใจเอง
Ziqi.
จื่อชี
I remember you've liked sour food since you were little.
ข้าจำได้ว่าเจ้าชอบกินของเปรี้ยวตั้งแต่เด็ก
These sour plum cakes are made
นี่คือขนมบ๊วยที่ทำจาก
from fresh seasonal plums.
บ๊วยสดตามฤดูกาล
Try some.
เจ้าลองชิมดูสิ
How is it?
เป็นอย่างไรบ้าง
When I was in the army,
ตอนที่ลูกอยู่ในกองทัพ
I missed your cooking.
ก็คิดถึงฝีมือทำอาหารของท่านแม่ขอรับ
Next,
แล้วหลังจากนี้
what are your plans?
เจ้าวางแผนไว้อย่างไร
Now that the three prefectures are settled,
ตอนนี้ดินแดนสามเมืองสงบลงแล้ว
my peace talks with Northern Qin are still ongoing—
การเจรจาสงบศึกกับเป่ยฉินยังคง...
Who asked about the peace talks?
ใครถามเรื่องเจรจาสงบศึกกัน
I'm asking about your marriage.
แม่ถามเรื่องคู่ครองของเจ้าต่างหาก
My proposal for reform
ข้าเสนอให้ปฏิรูป
touches the interests of noble families.
จึงกระทบผลประโยชน์ของตระกูลขุนนาง
The Empress Dowager hasn't declared her stance,
ไทเฮายังไม่แสดงท่าที
but she'll definitely have misgivings about the marriage
ต้องไม่พอพระทัยเรื่องการแต่งงานของ
between the He and Xiao families.
ตระกูลเหอกับตระกูลเซียวแน่
When the time is right,
เมื่อถึงเวลาที่เหมาะสม
I will end this marriage
ข้าจะยุติการแต่งงานครั้งนี้
and give He Yuanji her freedom,
คืนอิสระให้เหอหยวนจี
-so that she and Yao can— -Wuyi.
- และให้พี่ใหญ่กับนางได้... - อู๋อี
What I mean is,
ที่แม่หมายถึงก็คือ
life is a long journey.
เส้นทางชีวิตยังอีกยาวไกล
Walking hand in hand
คนสองคนจับมือกัน
beats going alone.
ย่อมดีกว่าเดินคนเดียวเสมอ
I really don't want you
แม่ไม่อยากให้เจ้า
to be truly alone.
ต้องไร้ที่พึ่งจริง ๆ
When you fell off your horse and fell into a coma that day,
วันที่เจ้าตกม้าจนสลบไป
Jiayu came to me
เจียอวี๋มาหาข้า
and told me to be fairer to you.
บอกให้ข้าปฏิบัติต่อเจ้าอย่างเป็นธรรมหน่อย
Although she doesn't know the whole story,
ถึงแม้นางจะไม่รู้เรื่องราวทั้งหมด
she can still see your difficulties.
แต่ก็มองออกว่าเจ้าลำบากใจ
I can see she's a good girl,
แม่ดูแล้ว นางเป็นเด็กดีนะ
and she cares for you.
และนางก็มีใจให้เจ้าด้วย
Xie Jiayu is pure and kind-hearted,
เซี่ยเจียอวี๋มีจิตใจดีโดยเนื้อแท้
but she already has someone she likes.
แต่นางมีคนที่ชอบอยู่แล้วขอรับ
So what?
แล้วอย่างไรล่ะ
Even if she's a kite in someone else's hands,
ต่อให้เป็นว่าวในมือของคนอื่น
if you like her,
ถ้าเจ้าชอบ
what's the harm in fighting for her?
ลองแย่งมาหน่อยจะเป็นไรไป
Besides, you now hold the string.
อีกอย่าง ตอนนี้เชือกก็อยู่ในมือเจ้า
In terms of status, you lose to no one.
ว่ากันตามฐานะแล้ว เจ้าไม่แพ้ใครเลยนะ
Are you telling me to snatch her?
ท่านแม่จะให้ข้าไปแย่งชิงหรือขอรับ
You're a grown man.
เป็นลูกผู้ชาย
What's the harm in fighting for her?
ช่วงชิงบ้างจะเป็นไรไป
But I promised Princess Yunzhao
แต่ข้าเคยรับปากท่านหญิงอวิ๋นเจาไว้
to give Xie Jiayu the freedom to choose.
ว่าจะให้อิสระในการเลือกแก่เซี่ยเจียอวี๋
You've met Princess Yunzhao?
เจ้าเจอท่านหญิงอวิ๋นเจาแล้วหรือ
For the path I must take,
เพื่อเส้นทางที่ข้าต้องเดิน
I've already dragged the Xiao family down.
ข้าลากตระกูลเซียวลงมาพัวพันแล้ว
I don't want to implicate anyone else.
ข้าไม่อยากให้คนอื่นต้องเดือดร้อนอีก
Darling!
ฮูหยิน
I caught a big fish!
ข้าตกปลาตัวใหญ่ได้ด้วยละ
Your son is useless.
ลูกชายเจ้าไม่ได้เรื่องเลย
He didn't even catch half a fish.
ตกไม่ได้สักตัว
Your father is really
พ่อของเจ้านี่จริง ๆ เลย
naughty by nature.
นิสัยขี้เล่นนัก
Come on.
มา
Let me refill your cup.
ข้าจะรินให้เจ้าอีกนะ
Okay.
ได้
I'll fill mine too.
งั้นข้าเอาด้วย
Yuezhou, one of the three prefectures awarded in this competition,
แคว้นเยว่ที่เป็นหนึ่งในสามเมือง ที่ชนะการประลองครั้งนี้
is where my husband died in battle.
คือสถานที่ที่สามีของข้าสิ้นชีพในสนามรบ
Ruisheng, I've heard you say this
พี่หญิง ท่านพูดเรื่องนี้
3 times already.
มาสามรอบแล้วนะ
I'm just happy.
ข้าดีใจนี่นา
If his spirit in heaven
หากวิญญาณของเขารับรู้ได้บนสวรรค์
knew that Yuezhou had returned to Ye,
ว่าแคว้นเยว่กลับคืนสู่ต้าเย่แล้ว
he would be thrilled.
เขาจะต้องดีใจมากแน่ ๆ
Then Ruisheng, was your husband
งั้นพี่หญิง สามีของท่าน
handsome?
หน้าตาหล่อเหลาหรือไม่
Of course.
แน่นอนอยู่แล้ว
Otherwise, why would I have chosen him?
ไม่อย่างนั้นข้าคงไม่เลือกเขาหรอก
He couldn't even afford the betrothal gifts then.
ตอนนั้นเขาไม่มีปัญญา หาของหมั้นมาให้ข้าด้วยซ้ำ
Is your man handsome?
แล้วคุณชายของเจ้าล่ะ หล่อเหลาหรือไม่
Right, is he handsome?
นั่นสิ หล่อเหลาหรือไม่
I understand.
เข้าใจแล้ว
If you think about it that way,
ถ้าท่านจะคิดแบบนั้นละก็
Xiao Wuyi is quite pitiful.
เซียวอู๋อีก็น่าสงสารแย่เลยสิ
He is so good at fighting.
รบเก่งขนาดนั้น
But he’s been married 3 times.
แต่เขาแต่งงานตั้งสามครั้ง
And no one wants him.
กลับไม่มีใครเอาเขาสักคน
-Coming. -Let me tell you.
- มาแล้ว - ข้าจะบอกอะไรให้
-He has a bad temper. -Let's go, Ziqi. Let's play in the water.
- เขาคนนี้อารมณ์ร้ายไปหน่อย - จื่อชี พวกเราไปเล่นน้ำกัน
-In fact, he is a good man. -Let's go, Ruisheng.
- แต่ที่จริงนิสัยเขาก็ไม่เลวนะ - ไป หรุ่ยเซิง
It's just that his temper is too bad.
แค่อารมณ์ร้ายไปหน่อย
Xie Jiayu,
เซี่ยเจียอวี๋
what did you just say about me?
เมื่อครู่เจ้าพูดอะไรถึงข้านะ
Ruisheng, I... I'll also go...
พี่หญิง เอ่อ ข้าไปด้วย
go...
ไป...
play in the water.
เล่นน้ำด้วย
Good. Very good.
ดี ดีมากเลย
I've never seen such a good person.
ไม่เคยเจอใครดีขนาดนี้มาก่อนเลย
What is this?
นี่คืออะไร
This is Li Lejun's new Four Pillars of Destiny Chart.
นี่คือวันเดือนปีเกิดใหม่ของหลี่เล่อจวิน
Whether from the perspective of Northern Qin
ไม่ว่าจะดูจาก
or Southern Ye's calendar and astrology,
ตำราโหราศาสตร์ของเป่ยฉินหรือของหนานเย่
hers and the Eagle King's are a sign of great misfortune.
ดวงชะตาของนางกับอิงอ๋องล้วน เป็นลางร้ายมหันต์
Put this in the royal genealogy.
เอาอันนี้ไปสับเปลี่ยนในสาแหรกราชวงศ์
I hope it can help her.
หวังว่าจะช่วยนางได้นะ
Okay, thanks.
ได้สิ ขอบคุณนะ
I've only been married once.
ข้าเคยแต่งงานแค่ครั้งเดียว
I don't need your pity.
ข้าไม่ต้องการให้เจ้ามาสงสาร
I
ข้า
do have a bad temper.
อารมณ์ร้ายจริง ๆ นั่นแหละ
No.
ไม่นะ
These are
นี่
my ideas for upgrading the Beifu weapons.
คือแนวคิดที่ข้ารวบรวมไว้ เพื่อดัดแปลงอาวุธของทัพเป๋ยฝู่
Some are already perfected,
บางส่วนสมบูรณ์แล้ว
and some still need work.
บางส่วนยังไม่สมบูรณ์พอ
On the day of the Double Ninth Ceremony,
ในวันพิธีหยางคู่
I promised the Beifu soldiers
ข้าเคยรับปากทัพเป๋ยฝู่ไว้
to upgrade their weapons.
ว่าจะดัดแปลงอาวุธให้พวกเขา
I will never break my promise.
ข้าจะไม่ผิดคำพูดเด็ดขาด
Well...
เอ่อ
most of the designs are whimsical.
การออกแบบส่วนใหญ่เพ้อฝันเกินจริง
But the talent is there.
แต่ก็ถือว่ามีพรสวรรค์อยู่บ้าง
Why don't you come with me to Beifu?
เจ้าตามข้าไปที่เป๋ยฝู่ดีหรือไม่
Designing weapons
การออกแบบอาวุธนี้น่ะ
is different from constructing mechanisms.
มันต่างจากกลไก
It requires examining the local terrain,
ต้องสำรวจลักษณะพื้นที่
weather, and tactics.
สภาพอากาศ และด้านการรบ...
Stop.
หยุด ๆ ๆ
I want to leave Xiao Wuyi,
ข้าจะไปจากเซียวอู๋อี
not be sold to him.
ไม่ใช่จะขายตัวให้เซียวอู๋อี
Besides, you just want to trick me into the Directorate of Military Equipment,
อีกอย่าง ท่านคิดจะหลอกข้าไปที่กองคลังอาวุธ
so you can slack off yourself, right?
แล้วตัวเองจะได้อู้งานใช่ไหมล่ะ
You.
เจ้านี่นะ
You are just like your mother.
เหมือนแม่ของเจ้าไม่มีผิด
You keep saying you want to roam the martial arts world
เอาแต่พูดว่าจะท่องยุทธภพ
and wander to the ends of the earth.
ร่อนเร่ไปสุดหล้าฟ้าเขียว
Then let me ask you, where is the martial arts world?
งั้นขอถามหน่อย ยุทธภพอยู่ที่ไหน
And where are the ends of the earth?
แล้วสุดหล้าฟ้าเขียวอยู่ที่ไหนกัน
-Martial arts world... -Look,
- ยุทธภพ... - เจ้าดูสิ
you can't answer, can you?
ตอบไม่ได้ใช่ไหมล่ะ
You just want to travel and play.
คิดแต่จะเที่ยวเล่นไปวัน ๆ
Let me tell you.
ข้าจะบอกให้นะ
At this time of year,
ช่วงเวลานี้
Heading south, there are rainstorms and floods.
ทางใต้มีพายุฝนน้ำท่วม
Heading north, there are sandstorms.
ทางเหนือมีพายุทราย
Heading west, there are high mountains and steep hills.
ทางตะวันตกมีแต่ภูเขาสูงชัน
Most importantly,
ที่สำคัญที่สุด
bandit rebellions occur from time to time.
คือมักจะมีโจรปล้นอยู่บ่อย ๆ
Still, I shouldn't be scared
ถึงอย่างนั้นก็จะกลัว
before I even go, right?
ทั้งที่ข้ายังไม่ได้ไปไม่ได้หรอก
That's true.
แน่นอน
Why don't you take me as your master?
เจ้ามาเป็นศิษย์ข้าดีกว่า
I'll take you to see
ข้าจะพาเจ้าไปดู
the desert roses
กุหลาบทะเลทราย
and yellow phosphorus mines you like.
เหมืองแร่หลินเหลืองที่เจ้าชอบ
Most importantly,
ที่สำคัญที่สุด
as your master, I
อาจารย์อย่างข้า
will pass on everything I've learned
จะถ่ายทอดวิชาความรู้ทั้งหมด
in my life to you,
ที่มีให้เจ้าเอง
making your mechanism designs
เพื่อที่การออกแบบกลไกของเจ้า
benefit the people's livelihood in the future.
จะได้เป็นประโยชน์ต่อผู้คนในอนาคตไง
Then...
แล้ว
can I bring a family member?
พาครอบครัวไปด้วยได้หรือไม่
I won't ask who this person is first.
ข้าขอยังไม่ถามนะว่าคนนั้นเป็นใคร
Is he willing?
เขาจะยอมไปหรือ
As a dignified man,
เป็นลูกผู้ชายทั้งคน
doesn't he have his own ambitions?
เขาจะไม่มีความทะเยอทะยานของตัวเองเลยหรือไร
He...
เขา
Picking a wife?
กำลังเลือกเมียอยู่หรือ
Thanks.
ขอบใจนะ
That Xie girl is so quick to catch on.
นางหนูเซี่ยนั่นฉลาดเป็นกรดเลย
After some persuasion from me,
หลังจากที่ข้าเกลี้ยกล่อมไป
she's already tempted
ตอนนี้นางก็เริ่มสนใจ
by the idea of becoming my disciple.
เรื่องการเป็นศิษย์ข้าแล้ว
Also,
แล้วก็
what amazing luck you have.
ดูโชคของท่านสิ
To have the heavens
ทำให้สวรรค์
send you such a treasure.
ส่งของล้ำค่าแบบนี้มาให้ได้
Do you look familiar?
คุ้นตาหรือไม่
Caltrop fireball.
หนามอัคคี
Xie tinkered with this herself
นี่เป็นสิ่งที่นางหนูเซี่ย อ่านเจอในตำราโบราณ
after reading ancient books.
แล้วก็ลองทำขึ้นมามั่ว ๆ
It perfectly matches
ตรงกับแนวคิดการออกแบบของข้า
my previous design ideas.
ก่อนหน้านี้ไม่มีผิด
Such talent
พรสวรรค์ระดับนี้
indeed shouldn't be buried
ไม่ควรจะถูกฝังไว้
in the romance of the inner quarters.
ท่ามกลางเรื่องรัก ๆ ใคร่ ๆ ในจวนจริง ๆ
You've really found a treasure.
ท่านได้ของดีแล้วนะ
[Divorce Agreement]
[หนังสือหย่า]
You like Xie Jiayu?
เจ้าชอบเซี่ยเจียอวี๋
Yes.
ใช่
Whether Xie Jiayu stays or leaves
เซี่ยเจียอวี๋จะไปหรืออยู่
is up to her as well.
ก็ให้นางเป็นคนตัดสินใจเอง
[Palace of Eternal Peace]
[ตำหนักหย่งอัน]
Her Majesty has selected some princesses for you, Your Highness.
ไทเฮาทรงคัดเลือกพระชายาให้ท่านอ๋องขอรับ
This is the legitimate daughter of Lord Liu, Vice Censor-in-Chief.
นี่คือบุตรีของใต้เท้าหลิวรองเจ้ากรมตรวจตรา
She is 15.
อายุสิบห้าปี
She is well-versed in poetry and books,
รอบรู้ในบทกวี
and is best at playing the guqin.
และดีดพิณได้ไพเราะที่สุด
This one is the niece of Lord Zhao, Director of the Secretariat.
ส่วนภาพนี้คือหลานสาวของใต้เท้าจ้าว แห่งสำนักราชเลขาธิการ
She has practiced martial arts since childhood.
ฝึกวรยุทธ์มาตั้งแต่เด็ก
She has a valiant temperament,
นิสัยห้าวหาญ
truly a heroine among women.
นับเป็นวีรสตรีในหมู่หญิง
Lejun.
เล่อจวิน
Come.
มานี่สิ
Do you think Yaoyao prefers moon white
เจ้าว่าเยาเยาชอบสีขาวนวล
or azure?
หรือสีฟ้าครามกัน
Let's wait for her to choose for herself.
หรือจะรอให้นางมาเลือกเองดี
Brother.
ท่านพี่
She usually likes to study those tools.
ปกติแล้วนางชอบประดิษฐ์สิ่งของพวกนั้น
But the palace has many rules,
แต่ในวังมีกฎระเบียบมากมาย
and it's not safe.
แล้วก็ไม่ปลอดภัย
I'm afraid it will be hard for her to enjoy herself.
เกรงว่าจะทำให้นางสนุกได้ไม่เต็มที่
She also likes to listen to storybooks.
นางยังชอบฟังนิยายด้วย
We can keep some entertainers
เราสามารถเลี้ยงคณะละครไว้แสดง
to make her happy.
ให้นางมีความสุขได้นะ
As for the Imperial Cuisine Department,
ทางห้องเครื่อง
I also sent someone to adjust
ข้าก็ให้คนไปจัดเตรียมตำรับอาหารใหม่
the menus according to her taste.
ตามที่นางชอบแล้ว
Hurry and help me think
เจ้าช่วยข้าคิดหน่อยสิ
if there's anything else I've missed.
ว่ามีอะไรตกหล่นอีกหรือไม่
Brother,
ท่านพี่
does Yaoyao know
เยาเยารู้หรือไม่
that you don't plan to leave Jiankang
ว่าท่านไม่คิดจะไปจากเจี้ยนคัง
but still want to bring her into the palace?
แต่กลับจะรับนางเข้าวัง
As long as I can be with her,
ขอแค่ข้าได้อยู่กับนาง
what difference does it make whether we leave Jiankang or not?
จะไปจากเจี้ยนคังหรือไม่มันจะต่างกันอย่างไร
How could there be no difference?
เหตุใดจะไม่ต่างกันเล่า
Yaoyao yearns for freedom,
เยาเยานางรักอิสระ
but you want her to live in the deep palace for a long time.
แต่ท่านกลับจะให้นางอยู่ในวังไปตลอดชีวิต
Don't you understand?
ท่านเข้าใจหรือไม่
Yaoyao can give up the name of Xie Jiayu
เยาเยาสามารถทิ้งชื่อเซี่ยเจียอวี๋
to travel the world with you.
ท่องยุทธภพไปกับท่านได้
But she won't give up the name of Xie Jiayu
แต่นางจะไม่ยอมทิ้งชื่อเซี่ยเจียอวี๋
to enter the palace with you.
เพื่อเข้าวังกับท่าน
Besides, there are these women.
อีกอย่าง ยังมีเรื่องพวกนี้อีก
These are all stopgap measures.
เรื่องพวกนี้เป็นเพียงแผนการชั่วคราว
Yaoyao will surely understand.
เยาเยาต้องเข้าใจแน่
[Prince Jing'an's Mansion]
[จวนจิ้งอันอ๋อง]
Over the past few days, one after another,
หลายวันมานี้มีตระกูลขุนนาง
prominent families have sent portraits to the Eastern Palace.
ส่งรูปวาดเข้าตำหนักบูรพาอย่างต่อเนื่อง
It seems they intend to propose marriage.
ดูเหมือนอยากจะแต่งงานเชื่อมสัมพันธ์
It looks like Prince Qi is determined not to leave.
ดูท่าฉีอ๋องจะตัดสินใจแน่วแน่แล้วว่าจะไม่ไป
Lady Xie is still in the dark.
แม่นางเซี่ยยังไม่รู้เรื่อง
These past few days, she's been busy preparing
หลายวันนี้กำลังยุ่งกับการจัดเตรียม
parting gifts for everyone in the mansion.
ของขวัญอำลาให้กับคนในจวนอยู่เลย
For the Heir's Consort,
ของชายาซื่อจื่อ
it's a paperweight.
คือที่ทับกระดาษอันหนึ่ง
For Madam Ruisheng,
ของหรุ่ยฮูหยิน
it's a brand-new set of acupuncture needles.
คือเข็มฝังเข็มชุดใหม่ล่าสุด
For the Prince and the Princess,
ส่วนของท่านอ๋องกับพระชายา
it's a suit of armor and a bladed hairpin.
คือชุดเกราะกับปิ่นปักผมรูปดาบ
A single slash severs the throat.
แค่ฟันฉับเดียว
The fastest way to slaughter a chicken.
ก็เชือดคอไก่ได้เร็วที่สุด
For Ziqi, it's a stack of
ของเซียวจื่อชีคือกอง
classic books she hasn't even finished reading herself.
หนังสือปราชญ์ที่นางเองก็ยังอ่านไม่จบ
That's it?
หมดแล้วเหรอ
Yan Yue and I got a pair of new shoes each.
ข้ากับเหยี่ยนเยว่ ได้รองเท้าใหม่คนละคู่ขอรับ
Calm down.
ใจเย็น ๆ ก่อน
Your Highness.
ซื่อจื่อเจ้าคะ
The Eagle King suddenly went back on his word.
อิงอ๋องกลับคำพูดกะทันหัน
He wants to add terms to the peace talks.
ต้องการเพิ่มเงื่อนไข ในข้อตกลงเจรจาสงบศึกเจ้าค่ะ
If you interrupt my medical practice again,
หากมารบกวนการรักษาของข้าอีก
you will have to find someone else.
ซื่อจื่อโปรดไปเชิญคนอื่นเถิด
He still hasn't given up.
ยังไม่ยอมแพ้อีกหรือ
What are his conditions?
เงื่อนไขของเขาคืออะไร
What is it?
มีเรื่องอะไร
Leave us.
พวกเจ้าออกไปให้หมด
Yes.
ขอรับ
Brother,
ท่านพี่
what happened?
เกิดเรื่องอะไรขึ้นหรือ
Lejun, did you meet the Eagle King once?
เล่อจวิน เจ้ากับอิงอ๋องเคยพบกันหรือไม่
Yes.
เคยเจ้าค่ะ
Why didn't you tell me earlier?
ทำไมเจ้าไม่บอกข้าให้เร็วกว่านี้
I thought he would make things difficult in public,
ข้าคิดว่าอิงอ๋องจะสร้างปัญหาต่อหน้าผู้คน
but he didn't mention it later.
แต่ต่อมาเขากลับไม่เอ่ยถึงเรื่องนี้
I thought the poisoning matter
ข้าคิดว่าเรื่องวางยาพิษ
couldn't be brought out into the open.
ก็ไม่ใช่เรื่องที่จะโอ้อวดได้
Her Majesty and the Eagle King
ไทเฮากับอิงอ๋อง
probably wouldn't do anything to me.
คงไม่ทำอะไรข้าหรอก
So I was relieved.
ก็เลยวางใจ
Why? Is the Eagle King
มีอะไรหรือ หรือว่าอิงอ๋อง
blackmailing you with this?
เขาใช้เรื่องนี้มาขู่ท่าน
The Eagle King intends to treat you as a princess
อิงอ๋องตั้งใจใช้เกียรติยศขององค์หญิง
for a political marriage with Northern Qin,
ให้เจ้าไปสมรสเชื่อมสัมพันธ์ที่เป่ยฉิน
to show the sincerity of the peace talks between the two countries.
เพื่อแสดงความจริงใจ ในการเจรจาสงบศึกของสองแคว้น
What?
อะไรนะ
Political marriage?
สมรสเชื่อมสัมพันธ์หรือ
Brother.
ท่านพี่
Don't worry, I will protect you.
วางใจเถอะ พี่จะปกป้องเจ้าเอง
I will never let you marry into Northern Qin.
ไม่มีทางให้เจ้าแต่งไปเป่ยฉินเด็ดขาด
[Ziji Palace]
[ตำหนักจื่อจี๋]
This is the legitimate daughter of Minister Cao, Commandant of Justice.
บุตรีภรรยาเอกของเสนาบดีตุลาการเฉา
She knows 6 languages
รู้ภาษาหกแคว้น
and can assist you with foreign affairs, Your Highness.
สามารถช่วยท่านอ๋องจัดการกิจการต่างแคว้นได้
This is the younger sister of the Left Palace Guard General.
ส่วนท่านนี้คือน้องสาวแท้ ๆ ของ ผู้บัญชาการราชองครักษ์ปีกซ้าย
She is excellent at brewing tea.
เก่งเรื่องชงชา
Upon tasting it, I find it surpasses the Nanzhao Xueya tea by quite a margin.
ข้าชิมแล้ว ยังอร่อยกว่า ชาหนานจ้าวเสวี่ยหยาเสียอีก
It seems
ดูท่า
it's hard for you to find a good match today.
วันนี้ท่านอ๋องคงจะหา คู่ครองที่เหมาะสมได้ยาก
He Tian, take everyone away.
เฮ่อเถียน พาพวกนางออกไปเถอะ
Yes.
พ่ะย่ะค่ะ
Take them all away.
พาตัวออกไปให้หมด
Sorry to trouble you, Your Majesty.
รบกวนไทเฮาแล้วพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
It's nothing.
ไม่เป็นไร
Although I couldn't find a good match for you today,
วันนี้แม้จะหาหญิงงามให้ท่านอ๋องไม่ได้
there is another excellent marriage arrangement.
แต่ยังมีเรื่องสมรสที่ดีเยี่ยมอีกคู่หนึ่ง
The day before yesterday,
เมื่อวันก่อน
the Eagle King sent an envoy to the palace,
อิงอ๋องส่งทูตพิเศษเข้าวังมา
who said the Eagle King admires Princess Pingning's virtues,
บอกว่าอิงอ๋องชื่นชมใน คุณธรรมของท่านหญิงผิงหนิง
is willing to offer the 1,000-li grassland in Monan as a betrothal gift,
ยินดีใช้ทุ่งหญ้าพันลี้ทางใต้ ของทะเลทรายเป็นสินสอด
and use the etiquette for a royal princess
ใช้เกียรติยศขององค์หญิง
to ask for the hand of your sister, Li Lejun.
สู่ขอน้องสาวของท่านอ๋อง หลี่เล่อจวิน
I think this is an excellent marriage arrangement,
ข้าคิดว่านี่เป็นการสมรสที่ดี
so I accepted the marriage document and betrothal gifts.
จึงรับหนังสือสมรสและสินสอดนี้ไว้
Please take a look.
ท่านอ๋องลองดูสิ
Recently, Northern Qin and our Ye
ช่วงนี้ เป่ยฉินกับต้าเย่ของเรา
are about to sign a peace treaty.
กำลังจะลงนามในสัญญาสันติภาพ
Our people at Northern Border
ราษฎรแดนเหนือของเรา
will no longer suffer from war.
ก็จะไม่ต้องทนทุกข์จากภัยสงครามอีก
If we can have a political marriage with Northern Qin,
หากสามารถสมรสเชื่อมสัมพันธ์กับเป่ยฉินได้
wouldn't it be a blessing for our people
จะไม่ใช่โชคดีของราษฎรเรา
and for Ye?
โชคดีของต้าเย่หรอกหรือ
Your Majesty, peace talks do not mean begging for peace.
ไทเฮา การเจรจาสันติภาพ ไม่ใช่การขอสันติภาพนะพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
If we just keep yielding,
หากเอาแต่ยอมอ่อนข้อ
it will only make Northern Qin more arrogant.
กลับจะทำให้เป่ยฉินยิ่งกำเริบ
Today, he dares to ask for my sister.
วันนี้เขากล้าขอน้องสาวกระหม่อม
Tomorrow, he will dare to ask for Jiankang.
พรุ่งนี้ก็คงกล้าขอเมืองเจี้ยนคัง
Please reconsider, Your Majesty.
ขอไทเฮาโปรดทบทวนด้วยพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
Reconsider?
ทบทวนหรือ
If I reconsider,
หากข้าคิดทบทวนอีก
Princess Pingning will have left the palace!
ท่านหญิงผิงหนิงก็คงหนีออกจากวังไปแล้ว
Bring her in!
พาตัวนางมาให้ข้า
Bring her in.
พาตัวมา
Today, I want to see
วันนี้ ข้าอยากจะดูนัก
who dares to take Li Lejun away
ว่าใครกล้าพาตัวหลี่เล่อจวินไป
and ruin the peace talks.
ทำลายการเจรจาสันติภาพ
Lejun!
เล่อจวิน
Brother.
ท่านพี่
Princess Pingning left the palace secretly,
ท่านหญิงผิงหนิงแอบหนีออกจากวัง
ruining the peace talks
ทำลายการเจรจาสันติภาพ
and disregarding the safety of Ye.
ไม่สนใจความปลอดภัยของต้าเย่
Beat her!
สั่งโบย
Lejun!
เล่อจวิน
Your Majesty!
ไทเฮาพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
I was the one who didn't want Lejun to enter a political marriage.
กระหม่อมไม่ยอมให้เล่อจวิน ไปสมรสเชื่อมสัมพันธ์เอง
I was the one who sent someone to take her out of the palace.
กระหม่อมสั่งให้คนส่งนางออกจากวัง
The one who should be beaten
คนที่ควรถูกโบย
should be me, Your Majesty!
ต้องเป็นกระหม่อมถึงจะถูกพ่ะย่ะค่ะ ไทเฮา
No,
ไม่นะ
that's not true.
ไม่ใช่เพคะ
Your Majesty, this has nothing to do with my brother.
ไทเฮา เรื่องนี้ไม่เกี่ยวกับ ท่านพี่ของหม่อมฉัน
I didn't want to marry the Eagle King,
หม่อมฉันไม่อยากสมรส เชื่อมสัมพันธ์กับอิงอ๋อง
so I ran away secretly.
จึงแอบหนีออกไปเองเพคะ
If you want to punish someone, punish me alone.
ไทเฮาจะลงโทษก็ลงโทษ หม่อมฉันคนเดียวเถอะเพคะ
Don't involve my brother.
อย่าได้พัวพันถึงท่านพี่ของหม่อมฉันเลย
Lejun.
เล่อจวิน
Brother.
ท่านพี่
I know
เล่อจวินรู้ดี
that you love me
ว่าท่านพี่สงสารเล่อจวิน
and want to take the blame for me.
อยากรับโทษแทนข้า
But you really knew nothing about this.
แต่เรื่องนี้ท่านพี่ไม่รู้เรื่องจริง ๆ
Your Majesty, I did all this alone.
ไทเฮาเพคะ เรื่องนี้เล่อจวินทำเพียงผู้เดียว
Please punish me.
ขอไทเฮาโปรดลงโทษด้วยเพคะ
Good.
ดี
What a deep bond between brother and sister.
ช่างเป็นพี่น้องที่รักกันดีจริง ๆ
Then I will grant your wish.
เช่นนั้นข้าจะทำให้พวกเจ้าสมหวัง
Prince Qi failed in his duty of supervision
ฉีอ๋องดูแลไม่ดี
and will receive 30 strokes of the cane.
สั่งโบยสามสิบที
Princess Pingning will take the punishment on behalf of her brother.
ให้ท่านหญิงผิงหนิงรับโทษแทนพี่ชาย
Mercy, Your Majesty!
ไทเฮา โปรดเมตตาด้วยพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
You can't do this, Your Majesty!
ไทเฮา ไม่ได้นะพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
Your Majesty!
ไทเฮา
-Lejun. -Pass my order.
เล่อจวิน N ถ่ายทอดคำสั่ง
Princess Pingning, Li Lejun,
ท่านหญิงผิงหนิง หลี่เล่อจวิน
with the rites of a princess,
ใช้เกียรติยศขององค์หญิง
shall marry the Eagle King of Northern Qin.
สมรสเชื่อมสัมพันธ์กับอิงอ๋องแห่งเป่ยฉิน
She is the pillar of our diplomatic relations
นับเป็นเสาหลักทางการทูต
and the core of the peace treaty.
เป็นกำลังสำคัญของการเจรจาสันติภาพ
Let the people of Jiankang decorate with flowers and lanterns,
ให้ขุนนางและราษฎรเจี้ยนคัง ประดับดอกไม้และผ้าสี
sweep the streets,
ทำความสะอาดถนนหนทาง
and celebrate the grand ceremony of her royal carriage's departure,
เพื่อร่วมเฉลิมฉลอง พิธีอภิเษกสมรสอันยิ่งใหญ่
to manifest the virtue of eternal peace between the North and South.
เพื่อแสดงถึงคุณูปการแห่งมิตรภาพ อันยั่งยืนของสองแคว้น
-Yes.
พ่ะย่ะค่ะ
Your Highness, are you here for the political marriage?
ท่านฉีอ๋องมาเพราะเรื่อง สมรสเชื่อมสัมพันธ์หรือ
Your Highness, I beg you to spare my sister.
ขอร้องอิงอ๋อง โปรดปล่อยน้องสาวข้าด้วยเถิด
Your Highness.
ท่านอ๋อง
Look at who these people are first.
ท่านดูคนพวกนี้ก่อนสิว่าเป็นใคร
These two are spies sent by you.
สองคนนี้เป็นไส้ศึกที่ฉีอ๋องส่งมา
For a bite of food and a sip of water,
พวกเขามีชีวิตอยู่อย่างเดรัจฉาน
they live like beasts of burden.
เพื่อข้าวคำ น้ำคำ
If your Southern Ye and our Northern Qin form a political marriage,
หากหนานเย่ของพวกท่าน กับเป่ยฉินของพวกเราได้ดองกัน
these people
คนพวกนี้
might live more like human beings.
อาจจะมีชีวิตเยี่ยงคนมากขึ้นก็ได้
So, Your Highness,
ดังนั้นท่านอ๋อง
between Princess Pingning and the beasts of burden,
ระหว่างท่านหญิงผิงหนิงกับพวกเดรัจฉาน
who would you choose?
ท่านจะเลือกใครกันล่ะ
And who would Xiao Wuyi choose?
แล้วเซียวอู๋อีจะเลือกใครกัน
But why does it have to be Lejun?
แต่เหตุใดต้องเป็นเล่อจวินด้วย
The political marriage
การสมรสเชื่อมสัมพันธ์
was not in the terms of the peace talks in the first place.
ก็ไม่ได้อยู่ในเงื่อนไข การเจรจาสันติภาพตั้งแต่แรก
I lost the competition,
ข้าแพ้การประลอง
and I am very unhappy.
ไม่สบอารมณ์อย่างมาก
That day, the Empress Dowager of your Southern Ye
วันนั้นไทเฮาแห่งหนานเย่ของพวกท่าน
prepared poison arrows,
เตรียมธนูอาบยาพิษไว้
which was truly disgraceful.
ช่างไร้ยางอายสิ้นดี
But your sister is quite interesting.
แต่น้องสาวของท่านน่าสนใจดีนะ
She broke the arrow.
นางหักลูกธนูทิ้ง
Even though she was in deep trouble,
ตัวเองตกอยู่ในอันตราย
she still wanted to save others.
ยังคิดจะช่วยคนอื่นอีก
Shouldn't such a stubborn flower
ดอกไม้ที่ดื้อรั้นเช่นนี้
bloom in the north wind,
ก็ควรจะเบ่งบานท่ามกลางลมเหนือ
should it?
มิใช่หรือ
You...
ท่าน
What are you doing?
ท่านทำอะไร
You're in the capital of Ye.
ที่นี่คือเมืองหลวงของต้าเย่นะ
Who can prove they are from Southern Ye?
ใครจะพิสูจน์ได้ว่าพวกเขาเป็นคนหนานเย่
Negotiations require bargaining chips.
การเจรจาต้องมีข้อแลกเปลี่ยน
In Northern Qin,
เป่ยฉินของพวกเรา
we respect heroes like Xiao Wuyi
นับถือคนอย่างเซียวอู๋อี
who have waded through mountains of swords and seas of blood.
ยอดคนที่ผ่านความเป็นความตายจนเป็นใหญ่
If he twists the truth out of thin air,
หากเขาบิดเบือนความจริงเพื่อพวกท่าน
who would dare to disagree in your Southern Ye court?
ราชสำนักหนานเย่ของพวกท่าน ใครจะกล้าไม่ยอมรับ
So, Prince Qi,
ดังนั้นฉีอ๋อง
what do you have?
ท่านมีอะไร
You are just an empty shell of a Regent,
ท่านเป็นเพียงผู้สำเร็จราชการที่ไร้อำนาจ
unfit to negotiate with me.
ไม่คู่ควรมาต่อรองกับข้า
I will not let my sister marry you.
ข้าไม่ยอมให้น้องสาวแต่งกับท่านเด็ดขาด
The day I became Regent,
วันที่ข้าได้เป็นผู้สำเร็จราชการ
who was the one who chose me?
คนที่เลือกข้า
Was it His Majesty
คือฝ่าบาท
or you, Master?
หรือว่าท่านอาจารย์กันแน่
It was me.
เป็นข้าเอง
Your Highness, can you tell me today
วันนี้ท่านอ๋องบอกข้าได้หรือไม่
if I made the wrong choice?
ว่าข้าเลือกคนผิดหรือเปล่า
What I learned in the past
สิ่งที่ศิษย์เคยเรียนมา
was all about the way of a gentleman
ล้วนเป็นวิถีแห่งบัณฑิต
and the principles of living.
หลักการในการดำเนินชีวิต
From now on,
นับจากนี้ไป
please teach me the way of a ruler
ขอท่านราชครูโปรดสอนวิถีแห่งราชา
and the art of an emperor.
และกลยุทธ์แห่งจักรพรรดิให้ข้าด้วย
Have you really thought it through,
คิดดีแล้วจริง ๆ หรือ
not to leave with Jiayu?
ไม่ไปกับเจียอวี๋แล้วหรือ
As long as I can save Lejun.
ขอเพียงช่วยเล่อจวินได้
This path is destined to only go forward,
เส้นทางนี้ถูกกำหนด ให้เดินไปข้างหน้าเท่านั้น
with no turning back.
ไม่มีทางให้ถอยกลับ
What is sincerity worth anyway?
ความจริงใจมันมีค่าอะไรกัน
How dare you come here and bargain with me?
ถึงได้กล้ามาต่อรองกับข้า
Everything you have now
เจ้ามีทุกสิ่งในวันนี้
was bestowed upon you by His Majesty and me.
ข้ากับฝ่าบาทประทานให้ทั้งนั้น
If I decide not to give it,
ถ้าข้าไม่อยากให้
then you shall have nothing.
จะไม่ให้ก็ได้
I want to have power.
ข้าอยากมีอำนาจ
I don't want to be empty-handed anymore,
ข้าไม่อยากไร้ซึ่งอำนาจ
threatened by others,
ให้ใครมาข่มขู่
and at their mercy.
หรือปล้นชิงไปง่าย ๆ
You and I both know well what Xiao Wuyi
เป้าหมายการปฏิรูปเป๋ยฝู่ ของเซียวอู๋อีคืออะไร
aims to achieve with his reform of Beifu.
ท่านกับข้าต่างก็รู้ดี
The peace talks are temporary.
การเจรจาสันติภาพเป็นเพียงเรื่องชั่วคราว
You're just taking advantage of the fact
ก็แค่อาศัยจังหวะที่การเมืองภายใน
that Northern Qin is currently in political chaos
เป่ยฉินของข้ากำลังวุ่นวาย
to gain some breathing room, aren't you?
เพื่อหาโอกาสหยุดพักหายใจมิใช่หรือ
If Xiao Wuyi really succeeds in the reform
หากเซียวอู๋อีผู้นี้ปฏิรูปได้สำเร็จ
and centralizes military power,
รวบอำนาจทหารไว้ในมือ
it will weaken the power of your noble families
ไม่เพียงจะลดทอนอำนาจตระกูลขุนนางของพวกท่าน
and pose a threat to our Northern Qin.
แต่ยังเป็นภัยคุกคามต่อเป่ยฉินของพวกเราด้วย
So, reasonably speaking,
ดังนั้นไม่ว่าจะด้วยเหตุหรือผล
we should cooperate.
ท่านกับข้าก็ควรจะร่วมมือกันนะ
You want me to commit treason?
ท่านจะให้ข้าทรยศต่อบ้านเมืองหรือ
Your Highness, having tea is fine,
ท่านอิงอ๋อง ดื่มชากันน่ะได้
but your appetite is too big.
แต่ความต้องการของท่านมันมากเกินไปแล้ว
And you can't give me what I want.
อีกอย่างท่านก็ให้ในสิ่งที่ข้าต้องการไม่ได้
What do you want?
ราชครูต้องการอะไรหรือ
The truth about
ความจริงของคดี
the treason case involving the An and Lu families
สมคบคิดกับศัตรูทรยศบ้านเมือง
of Ye 25 years ago.
ของตระกูลอันและลู่แห่งต้าเย่ เมื่อยี่สิบห้าปีก่อน
I can't help you with that.
เรื่องนี้ข้าช่วยท่านไม่ได้หรอก
I was just a child back then.
ตอนนั้นข้ายังเป็นเด็กน้อยอยู่เลย
Let the Empress Dowager of Northern Qin come talk to me.
ให้ไทเฮาแห่งเป่ยฉินมาคุยกับข้าสิ
She's in the Capital.
ไทเฮาอยู่ที่เมืองหลวง
Is she?
อย่างนั้นหรือ
Where else would she be?
แล้วจะให้เป็นอะไร
I can give you another greeting gift
ข้าสามารถให้ของขวัญแรกพบอีกอย่างแก่ท่านได้
to show my sincerity in cooperation.
เพื่อแสดงความจริงใจในการร่วมมือกัน
Xiao Wuyi.
เซียวอู๋อี
Whether the peace talks succeed or not,
ไม่ว่าการเจรจาสันติภาพจะสำเร็จหรือไม่
Li Lejun cannot marry.
หลี่เล่อจวินก็จะแต่งงานไม่ได้
The peace talks must succeed.
การเจรจาสันติภาพต้องสำเร็จ
I'm not asking you.
ข้าไม่ได้ถามเจ้า
I'm just telling you what I'm going to do.
ข้าแค่บอกเจ้าว่าข้าจะทำอะไรเท่านั้น
I know what the peace talks mean to you.
ข้ารู้ว่าการเจรจาสันติภาพ มีความหมายกับเจ้าเพียงใด
But Lejun is more important to me
แต่สำหรับข้าแล้วเล่อจวิน
than anyone else.
สำคัญกว่าใครทั้งนั้น
Your Highness, you should tell Prince Qi
ซื่อจื่อควรจะบอกท่านฉีอ๋องนะเจ้าคะ
that you're already figuring out a way.
ว่าท่านกำลังหาทางอยู่
The rift has already formed.
เมื่อเกิดความบาดหมางขึ้นแล้ว
There's no need to say more.
จะพูดไปไยให้มากความ
[Xiyue Restaurant]
[หอซีเยว่]
How is the investigation of the Northern Qin delegation going?
สืบเรื่องคณะทูตเป่ยฉินไปถึงไหนแล้ว
As you ordered, Your Highness,
ตามคำสั่งของซื่อจื่อ
I sent people to keep a close eye on Honglu Temple.
ข้าให้คนจับตาดูกรมพิธีการ
I also bought the night soil collector off.
และได้ติดสินบนคนเก็บมูลไว้แล้ว
Judging from the medicine dregs,
จากกากยาสามารถตรวจสอบได้ว่า
someone in the delegation must be seriously ill,
ในคณะทูตต้องมีคนป่วยหนักอยู่แน่
and it's an elderly woman.
และเป็นสตรีสูงวัย
Her status is quite high.
ที่มีฐานะสูงส่งมาก
Northwestern tiger bone.
กระดูกเสือจากซีเป่ย
Liaoshan ginseng.
โสมจากเขาเหลียว
South Sea agarwood.
ไม้กฤษณาจากทะเลใต้
Quite precious.
ล้วนล้ำค่าทั้งนั้น
This woman must have an extraordinary identity.
สตรีผู้นี้ต้องมีฐานะไม่ธรรมดาแน่
High status,
ฐานะสูงส่ง
yet not on the delegation's list.
แต่กลับไม่มีชื่ออยู่ในรายชื่อคณะทูต
Either the person's identity is inconvenient to reveal,
ถ้าไม่เพราะฐานะของผู้มาเยือนเปิดเผยไม่ได้
or their purpose is.
ก็เป็นจุดประสงค์ของผู้มาเยือน ที่เปิดเผยไม่ได้
Is this the great merit you mentioned?
นี่คือผลงานชิ้นใหญ่ที่เจ้าพูดถึงหรือ
There's more.
ไม่ใช่แค่นี้นะ
I had people watch for several days
ข้าให้คนสะกดรอยตามอยู่หลายวัน
before finally catching up with these two
ถึงได้ตามคนเป่ยฉินสองคน
Northern Qin people who went to the clinic to buy medicine.
ที่เข้าออกโรงหมอเพื่อซื้อยาทัน
Here comes the interesting part.
เรื่องสนุกมาแล้วขอรับ
Guess what?
ท่านทายสิว่าเป็นอย่างไร
These two Northern Qin people
ชาวเป่ยฉินสองคนนี้
-look familiar— -Spare me your storytelling.
- คุ้นหน้ายิ่งนัก - ข้าไม่ว่างมาฟังเจ้าเล่านิทานนะ
Get to the point.
เข้าประเด็นได้แล้ว
These two were once at Xiyue Restaurant,
สองคนนี้เคยไปหอซีเยว่
listening for several days
ติดต่อกันหลายวัน
to the storybooks of Crown Prince Wenxi.
เพื่อฟังนิทานเกี่ยวกับรัชทายาทเหวินซี
They also sent people to inquire
และยังเคยส่งคนไปสืบเรื่อง
about Crown Prince Wenxi and the Phoenix Heart Token.
รัชทายาทเหวินซีกับตรากระดูกปักษาด้วย
Great.
ดี
If the mountain won't come to me,
ในเมื่อภูเขาไม่มาหาข้า
I will go to the mountain.
ข้าก็จะไปหาภูเขาเอง
I'll use the Phoenix Heart Token to draw them out.
ใช้ตรากระดูกปักษาล่อเขาออกมา
Have Honglu Temple reorganize the peace talk proposals.
ให้กรมพิธีการทบทวนเงื่อนไข การเจรจาสันติภาพใหม่
Apart from the three prefectures,
นอกจากดินแดนสามเมืองแล้ว
see if there is any room for negotiation.
ดูว่ายังมีช่องว่างให้เจรจาต่อรองอีกหรือไม่
The Eagle King just wants to prove a point.
อิงอ๋องก็แค่ต้องการเอาชนะเท่านั้นแหละ
The Eagle King has always wanted the smelting technique for refined iron,
อิงอ๋องต้องการวิชาหลอมเหล็กชั้นดีมาตลอด
even offering 800 fine horses in exchange.
ถึงขนาดยอมใช้ยอดอาชาแปดร้อยตัวมาแลก
This is non-negotiable.
ข้อนี้ไม่มีทางเด็ดขาด
Spit it out.
พูดมาสิ
Spit what out?
พูดอะไรหรือ
Words to scold me.
ก็ด่าข้าไง
Haven't you heard the news?
เจ้าได้ยินข่าวแล้วไม่ใช่หรือ
I did have a lot to say to scold you.
มีเรื่องอัดอั้นอยากจะด่าท่าน เต็มไปหมดจริง ๆ
But you look so weighed down with troubles.
แต่เห็นท่านกำลังกลุ้มใจอยู่
Never mind.
ช่างเถอะ
What did Mao say?
อาเม่าว่าอย่างไรบ้าง
He won't let Li Lejun enter a political marriage, no matter what,
ไม่ว่าอย่างไรเขาก็ไม่ยอมให้หลี่เล่อจวิน ไปสมรสเชื่อมสัมพันธ์
at any cost.
ไม่ว่าจะต้องแลกด้วยอะไรก็ตาม
Mao and Lejun only have each other.
อาเม่ากับเล่อจวินพึ่งพากันและกันมาตลอด
It's only right for him to do so.
เขาสมควรทำเช่นนั้น
But to you, Xiao Wuyi,
แต่สำหรับท่านเซียวอู๋อีแล้ว
ensuring the peace talks go smoothly
การทำให้การเจรจาสันติภาพราบรื่น
and buying time for the Beifu reform
เพื่อให้มีเวลาปฏิรูปเป๋ยฝู่
are the most important things.
คือสิ่งที่สำคัญที่สุด
Yes.
ใช่
Though,
ถึงแม้ว่า
you know what Lejun will face.
ท่านจะรู้ว่าเล่อจวินต้องเจอกับอะไร
All right.
ก็ได้
That's it?
แค่นี้หรือ
I thought you would argue with me,
ข้านึกว่าเจ้าจะทะเลาะกับข้า
calling me a liar, cold-blooded,
ด่าข้าว่าเป็นคนหลอกลวง เลือดเย็น
and worse than a beast.
เลวร้ายยิ่งกว่าสัตว์เดรัจฉาน
Xiao Wuyi,
เซียวอู๋อี
in your heart,
ในใจของท่าน
am I that unreasonable?
ข้าดูไม่มีเหตุผลมากเลยใช่หรือไม่
Have you ever been reasonable with me?
หรือว่าเมื่อก่อนเจ้าเคยมีเหตุผลกับข้า
You have already changed Lejun's birth records.
ท่านเปลี่ยนวันเดือนปีเกิดของเล่อจวิน ในสาแหรกราชวงศ์ให้แล้ว
You've done all you can.
สิ่งที่ทำได้ท่านก็ทำหมดแล้ว
The instigator today is the Eagle King.
เรื่องในวันนี้ต้นเหตุก็คืออิงอ๋อง
You only made your choice.
ท่านเป็นแค่คนที่ต้องรับผิดชอบในการตัดสินใจ
You are not to blame.
เรื่องนี้จะโทษท่านไม่ได้หรอก
What's with that look?
ท่านทำหน้าอะไรของท่านน่ะ
Nothing.
เปล่านี่
I don't know either.
ข้าก็ไม่รู้เหมือนกัน
Probably because
คงเป็นเพราะว่า
it's the first time I've heard someone say that,
เพิ่งเคยได้ยินคนพูดแบบนี้เป็นครั้งแรก
so it feels fresh.
เลยรู้สึกแปลกใหม่กระมัง
However,
แต่ว่า
I will still stop this.
ข้าก็จะขัดขวางเรื่องนี้อยู่ดี
If Lejun were a pampered princess
ถ้าเล่อจวินเป็นองค์หญิง ที่ถูกเลี้ยงดูอย่างตามใจมาตั้งแต่เด็ก
supported by the people,
ได้รับการปรนนิบัติจากราษฎร
then she would shoulder the responsibility of the world now,
ตอนนี้จะให้นางแบกรับ ความรับผิดชอบต่อแผ่นดิน
and I'd have nothing to say.
ข้าก็ไม่มีอะไรจะพูด
But she is not.
แต่นางไม่ใช่
Qizhou fell.
ฉีโจวล่มสลาย
Mao and Lejun fled all the way
อาเม่ากับเล่อจวินหนีตายมาตลอดทาง
to Jiankang.
จนมาถึงเจี้ยนคัง
Did His Majesty and Her Majesty
ฝ่าบาทกับไทเฮา
ever care for them for a single day?
เคยดูแลพวกเขาบ้างไหม
They only have the status of the royal family in name,
มีแค่สถานะเชื้อพระวงศ์
but live worse than ordinary people.
แต่กลับมีความเป็นอยู่ สู้ชาวบ้านธรรมดาก็ไม่ได้
To support the family,
เพื่อหาเลี้ยงครอบครัว
Lejun has been copying books for others
เล่อจวินต้องคัดลอกหนังสือ ให้คนอื่นตั้งแต่เด็ก
and doing needlework since childhood.
ทำงานเย็บปักถักร้อย
She was already weak.
นางร่างกายอ่อนแออยู่แล้ว
If my mother hadn't known some medical skills
ถ้าไม่ใช่เพราะท่านแม่ของข้า พอมีความรู้ทางการแพทย์
and hadn't found out Lejun had an old illness,
พบว่าเล่อจวินมีโรคประจำตัว
she would have barely survived.
นางคงเกือบไม่รอดชีวิตแล้ว
This is not the ending a good person should have.
นี่ไม่ใช่จุดจบที่คนดี ๆ ควรได้รับ
How do you plan to stop it?
แล้วเจ้าคิดจะขัดขวางอย่างไร
Don't worry.
ท่านวางใจเถอะ
My method
วิธีของข้า
has nothing to do with your empire.
ไม่เกี่ยวกับใต้หล้าของท่าน
Being your friend
การเป็นสหายกับเจ้า
is quite lucky.
ช่างโชคดีนัก
You forgot.
ท่านลืมแล้วหรือ
You are also my friend.
ท่านก็เป็นสหายของข้าเช่นกัน
♪ A dying memory glimmers low ♪
♪ เฝ้ามองความทรงจำที่เลือนราง ♪
♪ You appear, but I can't hold you so ♪
♪ ท่านปรากฏขึ้น แต่กลับไกลเกินเอื้อมถึง ♪
I'm here to save you!
ข้ามาช่วยเจ้าแล้ว
♪ Time itself comes to a sudden halt ♪
♪ เวลาพลันหยุดหมุนไปชั่วขณะ ♪
♪ So desolate ♪
♪ โดดเดี่ยวเหลือเกิน ♪
♪ I traded obsession for this loss ♪
♪ ความสูญเสียที่เกิดจากการยึดติด ♪
Someone like you
คนอย่างท่าน
♪ If I could lay my heart bare and cross ♪
♪ หากข้าผ่าเปิดหัวใจดวงนี้ได้ ♪
is born to be on the battlefield,
เกิดมาเพื่ออยู่ในสนามรบ
to make everyone fear you.
ทำให้ทุกคนเกรงกลัวท่าน
♪ Would you once more have pity on me ♪
♪ ท่านจะยอมทะนุถนอมอีกครั้งหรือไม่ ♪
♪ If the heavens should change and fate tear me apart ♪
♪ หากชะตาฟ้าดินพลิกผันจนข้าแหลกสลาย ♪
♪ Yet still cannot undo one beat of my heart's art ♪
♪ กลับทำลายความคิดถึงไม่ได้ แม้เพียงเสี้ยว ♪
♪ I've traveled so far— the day I find you again ♪
♪ เดินทางมาไกลแสนไกล วันที่ได้พบท่านอีกครั้ง ♪
♪ I fear you might have forgotten me ♪
♪ ข้ากลัวว่าท่านจะลืมเลือน ♪
If you trust me,
หากท่านเชื่อใจข้าละก็
♪ I fear no doom of endless karmic pain ♪
♪ ข้าไม่กลัวภัยพิบัติจริง ♪
let me be your eyes.
ให้ข้าเป็นดวงตาให้ท่านเอง
♪ Only that you drift far from my side ♪
♪ เกรงว่าเจ้าจะไปไกล ♪
♪ Apart from you, the world is an endless night ♪
♪ ข้าจากเจ้าไป โลกเหลือเพียงคืนนิรันดร์ ♪
♪ Even if my beating heart wears thin and fades ♪
♪ ถึงแม้ว่าหัวใจจะเต้นจนหมดแรง ♪
♪ I'd choose this fate till death's final line ♪
♪ ก็ยอมตาย ♪
You forgot.
ท่านลืมแล้วหรือ
You are also my friend.
ท่านก็เป็นสหายของข้าเช่นกัน
♪ I only hope the mortal lands ♪
♪ ข้าเพียงหวังว่าแดนมนุษย์ ♪
♪ Can grant our wishes ♪
♪ จะช่วยให้เราสมหวัง ♪
It's quite hard to let go.
รู้สึกใจหายเหมือนกันนะ
♪ Through endless night, let heaven and earth fall apart ♪
♪ ขั้นด้วยคืนนิรันดร์ ก็ยอมให้ฟ้าดินล่มสลาย ♪
♪ I'd bid farewell to every worldly part ♪
♪ แค่อยากบอกลาทุกสิ่ง ♪
♪ Just to gaze upon you one last time ♪
♪ ไปพบเจ้าอีกครา ♪
Have you done what I told you?
เรื่องที่ข้าสั่งให้เจ้าไปทำ เรียบร้อยแล้วใช่หรือไม่
As you instructed, My Lady,
ทำตามที่คุณหนูสั่งแล้วเจ้าค่ะ
the item has been delivered to the Eagle King.
ส่งของถึงมืออิงอ๋องแล้ว
Good.
ดี
If anyone asks later,
ประเดี๋ยวถ้ามีคนมาถาม
just say I went to the South Street Bookstore
เจ้าก็บอกว่าข้าไปซื้อหนังสือ ให้พี่หญิงหยวนจี
to buy books for Yuanji.
ที่ร้านหนังสือทางถนนใต้นะ
You don't know anything else.
นอกนั้นก็ไม่รู้อะไรทั้งสิ้น
-Especially don't let Xiao Wuyi know. -Morning.
- โดยเฉพาะห้ามให้เซียวอู๋อี๋รู้ - อรุณสวัสดิ์
What are you doing?
ท่านจะทำอะไร
Where are you going?
จะไปไหน
First to the South Street Bookstore
ไปร้านหนังสือที่ถนนใต้ก่อน
to buy books for Yuanji,
เพื่อช่วยพี่หญิงหยวนจีซื้อหนังสือ
then to Renhe Hall
แล้วไปที่ร้านเหรินเหอถัง
to fetch the newly arrived cassia seeds for Ruisheng.
เพื่อเอาเมล็ดชุมเห็ดเทศ ที่เพิ่งมาใหม่ไปให้พี่หญิงหรุ่ยเซิง
After that, to Xinghua Restaurant
จากนั้นค่อยไปที่หอซิ่งฮวา
to buy mint cakes for Ziqi.
เพื่อซื้อขนมสะระแหน่ให้จื่อชี
What about you? Where are you going?
แล้วท่านล่ะ จะไปไหน
To the palace
เข้าวัง
to continue discussing the peace talks with Northern Qin.
ไปหารือเรื่องข้อตกลงสันติภาพกับเป่ยฉินต่อ
After you.
ถ้าอย่างนั้นเชิญท่านก่อนเลย ๆ
Your business is more important.
เรื่องของท่านสำคัญกว่า
I won't bother you.
ข้าไม่รบกวนท่านแล้ว
[Xiyue Restaurant]
[หอซีเยว่]
-Great!
- ดี
During the storytelling just now,
เมื่อครู่ตอนเล่านิทาน
you said you had seen the Phoenix Heart Token.
เจ้าบอกว่าเคยเห็นตรากระดูกปักษาหรือ
Of course.
แน่นอนอยู่แล้ว
Come with me.
ไป ตามข้ามา
[Honglu Temple]
[กรมพิธีการ]
Xiao Wuyi's little beauty.
คนงามของเซียวอู๋อีนี่เอง
What a rare guest.
ผู้มาเยือนที่หาได้ยาก
You sent someone to deliver refined iron to me.
เจ้าใช้คนส่งเหล็กชั้นดีมาให้ข้า
What's the meaning of this?
หมายความว่าอย่างไร
Where did this come from?
เอามาจากไหน
I smelted it.
ข้าหลอมเอง
First, forged at a high temperature
เริ่มจากหลอมด้วยอุณหภูมิสูง
to remove all impurities,
กำจัดสิ่งเจือปนออกให้หมด
then quenched in green liquor.
แล้วชุบให้แข็งด้วยน้ำสีเขียวจึงได้มา
I know
ข้ารู้
you want the smelting technique for refined iron.
ว่าท่านต้องการวิชาหลอมเหล็กชั้นดี
Are you really going to give me the refined iron?
เจ้าให้เหล็กชั้นดีกับข้าจริง ๆ หรือ
Not exactly.
ก็ไม่เชิง
I just used this refined iron as bait
ข้าแค่ใช้เหล็กชั้นดีนี้เป็นเหยื่อล่อ
to lure you to meet me.
เพื่อให้ท่านมาพบข้า
Are you playing me?
เจ้าหลอกข้าหรือ
I wouldn't dare.
มิกล้า ๆ
Princess Pingning is my close friend.
ท่านหญิงผิงหนิงเป็นสหายรักของข้า
So it's about this.
ที่แท้ก็เรื่องนี้เอง
I didn't expect Princess Pingning's life
ไม่นึกเลยว่าชีวิตของท่านหญิงผิงหนิง
to be quite valuable.
จะมีค่าขนาดนี้
You want to marry Pingning
ที่ท่านอยากแต่งกับผิงหนิง
just to vent your anger
ก็เพียงเพราะต้องการระบายความโกรธ
and regain dignity.
เพื่อรักษาหน้าตัวเองเท่านั้น
If you are interested in the smelting technique for refined iron,
หากท่านสนใจวิชาหลอมเหล็กชั้นดี
then I'll make a deal with you.
งั้นข้าขอต่อรองกับท่าน
No,
ไม่สิ
a business.
ขอแลกเปลี่ยน
I'm all ears.
ข้าอยากจะฟังรายละเอียด
Your Majesty.
ไทเฮาพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
[Shao Yang, the Empress Dowager of the Northern Qin]
[เส้ายาง ไทเฮาแห่งเป่ยฉิน]
I've heard so much about you.
ได้ยินชื่อเสียงมานาน
I thought I caught someone's slip-up,
นึกว่าจับพิรุธคนอื่นได้แล้ว
but I didn't expect
คาดไม่ถึงว่า
that it was I who made a mistake.
กลับเป็นตัวเองที่เผยพิรุธออกมา
Your Highness, if you hadn't
หากไม่ใช่เพราะก่อนหน้านี้ซื่อจื่อ
eliminated Northern Qin's spy strongholds,
ทำลายฐานสายลับเป่ยฉินของข้า
these two fools
เจ้าโง่สองคนนี้
wouldn't have been discovered so easily.
ก็คงไม่ถูกซื่อจื่อจับได้ง่าย ๆ
Being a spy
การเป็นสายลับเนี่ย
still needs experience.
อย่างไรก็ต้องมีประสบการณ์สินะ
Why did you come here, Your Majesty?
ไทเฮาทรงทำเช่นนี้เพื่อสิ่งใด
Is it also for the Phoenix Heart Token?
หรือว่าก็เพื่อตรากระดูกปักษาเหมือนกัน
If I say
ถ้าข้าบอกว่า
I got tired of the Capital
เบื่อเมืองหลวงแล้ว
and came to Southern Ye to enjoy the scenery,
เลยมาชมทิวทัศน์ที่หนานเย่
will you believe me?
ซื่อจื่อจะเชื่อหรือไม่
I won't.
ไม่เชื่ออยู่แล้วพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
Then that's the only excuse I have.
งั้นข้าก็มีแค่เหตุผลนี้เท่านั้นละ
Speak.
ว่ามาเถอะ
Your Highness, why did you want to see me?
ซื่อจื่อต้องการพบข้าด้วยเรื่องอันใด
Are you trying to tell me
หรือว่าอยากจะบอกข้าว่า
where the Phoenix Heart Token is?
ตรากระดูกปักษาอยู่ที่ไหน
I hope you can stop the Eagle King
หวังว่าไทเฮาจะขัดขวางอิงอ๋อง
from marrying Princess Pingning.
ไม่ให้สมรสกับท่านหญิงผิงหนิง
A political marriage between Northern Qin and Ye is a long-term strategy.
การสมรสเชื่อมสัมพันธ์ ของฉินและเย่เป็นแผนระยะยาว
You have been in the military for years.
ซื่อจื่ออยู่ในสนามรบมาหลายปี
Don't you understand
จะไม่เข้าใจได้อย่างไร
that peace benefits both?
ว่าการปรองดองมีแต่ได้กับได้
You must know better than I do
ไทเฮาคงจะรู้ดีกว่ากระหม่อม
that the emperor of Northern Qin and the Eagle King
ว่าฝ่าบาทเป่ยฉินกับอิงอ๋อง
are only sovereign and subject on the surface.
เป็นเพียงกษัตริย์กับขุนนางแต่ในนาม
The Eagle King has heavily armed himself,
อิงอ๋องมีกองกำลังในมือ
and you support the emperor.
ไทเฮาคอยค้ำจุนบัลลังก์
That's why the Northern Qin court is stable.
ราชสำนักเป่ยฉินจึงได้สงบสุข
But if you pass away
แต่ถ้าหากไทเฮาสวรรคต
and the Eagle King forms a marriage alliance with Ye,
แล้วอิงอ๋องได้สมรสกับต้าเย่
marrying the sister of the current Regent,
ทั้งยังได้สมรสกับน้องสาวแท้ ๆ ของฉีอ๋อง
Prince Qi,
ผู้สำเร็จราชการคนปัจจุบัน
once he has Jiankang's help,
เมื่อได้รับการสนับสนุนจากเจี้ยนคัง
the balance will be broken.
ความสมดุลก็จะถูกทำลาย
In that case,
เช่นนี้แล้ว
how can you guarantee
จะรับประกันได้อย่างไร
the Eagle King's troops
ว่ากองกำลังของอิงอ๋อง
will still be Northern Qin's sword?
จะยังคงเป็นดาบอันแหลมคมของเป่ยฉิน
You make a valid point.
ซื่อจื่อพูดมีเหตุผลนะ
But even if my son and I have disagreements with the Eagle King,
แต่ถึงแม้ว่าเราแม่ลูกจะไม่ลงรอยกับอิงอ๋อง
it's not for an outsider to manipulate.
ก็ไม่ถึงตาคนนอกมาบงการกระมัง
Such an obvious attempt to sow discord—
แผนยุยงที่เห็นได้ชัดขนาดนี้
are you being too impatient?
ซื่อจื่อใจร้อนเกินไปหน่อยหรือไม่
Just a suggestion.
เป็นเพียงข้อเสนอแนะเท่านั้น
Your Majesty.
ไทเฮาเพคะ
Thank you for your kindness, Your Highness.
ขอบคุณในความหวังดีของซื่อจื่อ
Then I will also tell you something.
งั้นข้าก็จะบอกเรื่องหนึ่งให้ซื่อจื่อรู้
Your Secondary Consort, Xie Jiayu,
ชายารองของท่าน เซี่ยเจียอวี๋
for the political marriage,
ก็กำลังหารือเรื่องสมรสเชื่อมสัมพันธ์
is secretly meeting the Eagle King at Honglu Temple right now.
กับอิงอ๋องอย่างลับ ๆ ที่กรมพิธีการ
I heard
ได้ยินว่า
she also prepared a big gift for the Eagle King.
ยังเตรียมของขวัญชิ้นใหญ่ให้อิงอ๋องด้วยนะ
Please wait, Your Highness.
ท่านอ๋องโปรดช้าก่อน
I have shown my sincerity.
เมื่อครู่ข้าได้แสดงความจริงใจแล้ว
I hope you can carefully consider the political marriage
หวังว่าท่านอ๋องจะพิจารณา เรื่องสมรสเชื่อมสัมพันธ์อย่างรอบคอบ
and make a good deal with me.
และทำการแลกเปลี่ยนที่คุ้มค่ากับข้า
I'll await your good news.
เจียอวี๋จะรอฟังข่าวดีเจ้าค่ะ
I won't see you out.
ส่งแค่นี้นะ
No need to see me out. Go back.
ไม่ต้องส่งแล้ว ท่านกลับไปเถอะ
Excuse me.
ขอโทษด้วยนะ
Still acting?
ยังจะแสดงอีก
Since when has the South Street Bookstore been open in Honglu Temple?
ร้านหนังสือถนนใต้มาเปิดใน กรมพิธีการตั้งแต่เมื่อใด
Well, I was just...
เอ่อ ข้าแค่...